Guide to the Benson Family Photographs Collection 1896-1970
Oregon Historical Society, Research Library
Benson family photographs collection
1896-1970
Oregon Historical Society, Davies Family Research Library Research Library 1200 SW Park Avenue Portland, Oregon 97205 Phone: 503-306-5240 Fax: 503-219-2040 E-mail: libreference@ohs.org
Org. Lot 1206
Benson family
3 cubic ft. 7 document cases and 2 flat boxes
Photographs of the family of Portland businessman Simon Benson and his second wife, Pamela Loomis, including sons Chester Simon Benson and Gilbert Thereon Benson, and grandchildren Gilbert Thomas Benson and Margaret Benson Maradudin.
Biographical Note
Simon Benson (1851-1942), a Norwegian immigrant, found considerable success in the innovative management of his substantial timber holdings. He also built the Benson and Columbia Gorge Hotels, and as a strong proponent of the good roads movement, propelled development of the Columbia River Highway. His second marriage, to Pamela Loomis, produced two sons, Gilbert Thereon and Chester Simon. Gilbert died in 1928, well into graduate studies at Stanford University. Chester married Dorothy Logan, and together they raised son Gilbert Thomas and daughter Margaret (Maradudin).
Collection consists of photographs of the family of Portland businessman Simon Benson and his second wife, Pamela Loomis, including Simon Benson, his sons Chester Simon Benson and Gilbert Thereon Benson, and grandchildren Gilbert Thomas Benson and Margaret Benson Maradudin. Includes baby albums and portraits, as well as photographs depicting travel, boating, Stanford University, California, Oregon Coast, Columbia River Gorge, and Benson family residences in Portland as well as their summer cottage, Riverwood, in Lake Oswego, Oregon.
The collection is arranged in the following series:
Series A: Photographic prints
Series B: Photo albums
Series C: Unprocessed Negatives
The collection is open to the public.
Lib. Acc. 27705
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Benson family--Photographs; Benson, Gilbert Thereon, 1896-1928 --Photographs; Benson, Chester Simon, 1902-1971--Photographs; Benson, Gilbert Thomas, 1929-2011--Photographs; Maradudin, Margaret Benson--Photographs; Benson, Simon, 1851-1942--Photographs
Benson family--Homes and haunts--Photographs
Stanford University--Photographs
Portland (Or.)--Photographs; Lake Oswego (Or.).--Photographs; Columbia River Gorge (Or.and Wash.)--Photographs; Pacific Coast (Or.)--Photographs
Buildings, structures, etc. -- Photographs; Boats and boating -- Photographs; Voyages and travels -- Oregon--Photographs; Voyages and travels -- California--Photographs; College life--Photographs; Children--Oregon--Photographs
Home and Family; Oregon; Photographs
Photographic prints; Photograph albums
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Photographic prints, 1896-1970; Series A; 1.1 cubic ft. (3 document cases and 1 oversize folder)
  - Mr. & Mrs. Simon Benson portraits, 1896; undated (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Aerial views, undated (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Airplanes, Airport, undated (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Automobiles, 1920s (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Babies, circa 1910-1970 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Benson Place (Riverwood House), undated (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Boating, undated (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Boats, undated (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Boats and airplanes, 1920s (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Buildings, 1920s (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Buildings, unknown Southwest locations, undated (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Cabins, undated (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Children, circa 1920-1970 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Christmas, 1967 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Columbia Gorge Hotel (Hood River, Or.), 1921 July 8 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Columbia River Gorge, 1920 August (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Death Valley, circa 1930; Stock photos and photo postcards from Frashers Foto - Pomona (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Gardens, undated; Related to Benson Place (Riverwood House) photos in 1/6. (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Hawaii, 1920s or 1930s (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Horses - jumping and racing, undated (Box-folder 1/20)
  - House interiors, undated (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Houses, undated (Box-folder 1/22)
  - People, 1920s (Box-folder 2/1)
  - People and pets, undated (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Pets, circa 1920s-1970 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - Photo booklet, 1961 October (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Photographs developed in Paris, 1920s (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Photo strips, undated (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Sailboats, undated (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Seaside bath house, undated (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Southwest Indian ruins and other photos, 1960 July (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Tintype (cased) - Portrait of unidentified woman, undated (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Travel album: Quebec, Mt. Rainier, and other scenes, 1940s (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Unidentified photos, 1960 May (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Views and miscellaneous objects, circa 1920s (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Wildlife, undated (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Yosemite, undated (Box-folder 2/15)
  - Portraits removed from frame, 1914 May (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Scenic views, circa 1920s (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Unidentified people, 1920s-1970s (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Unidentified portraits, circa 1900-1950 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Unidentified photos, circa 1910s-1950s (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Letter to Chester Benson from Betty (Honolulu, Hawaii), with photographs, 1925 May 1 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Photo postcards, 1940; undated (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Business and membership cards, 1971; undated (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Selected negative envelopes and inserts, circa 1920-1960 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Oversize portraits (includes Chester Benson), circa 1940 (Box-folder 8/1)
- Photo albums, 1899-1940; Series B; 1.72 cubic ft. (3 document cases and 2 flat boxes)
  - Album 2 - Chester Benson, 1915-1920 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Album 3 - Unidentified, circa 1939 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Album 4 - Gilbert Thereon Benson - Riverwood House (Lake Oswego, Or.), 1919-1921 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Album 5 - Gilbert Thereon Benson - Stanford, California, and Pacific Northwest scenes, 1918-1921 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Album 6 - possibly Margaret Benson, circa 1940 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Album 7 - Gilbert Thomas Benson - Baby album, 1929-1932 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Album 8 - probably Gilbert Thomas Benson & Margaret Benson - Baby album, approx. 1929-1935 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Album 9- Chester Benson, 1920s (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Album 10 - Cabinet card portraits, 1899; undated (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Album 10 (empty), 1899 (Box-folder Box 7)
  - Album 1 - Chester Benson family, including Gilbert Thomas Benson, circa 1930-1940 (Box-folder Box 8)
  - Album 11 - Riverwood House (Lake Oswego, Or.) - includes Chester Benson, et al, possibly 1920s (Box-folder Box 8)
- Unprocessed Negatives, circa 1920s; undated; Series C; 0.18 cubic ft. (1 document case)
  This box is stored offsite. Access is restricted and requires special arrangements with library staff.
  - Roll of nitrate negative film, undated (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Assorted negatives, undated (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Assorted negatives, circa 1920s (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Assorted negatives, circa 1920s (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Best of S.L.C., undated (Box-folder 9/5)
  - Boating, undated (Box-folder 9/6)
  - Grandma's, 295 Front St., circa 1920s (Box-folder 9/7)